reminder that your final
in this class
so he has started
the trainer
conspiracy here first
which search
tools
so they weren't cover since i was a
little bit different for starters
program began
talking about copyright
it's and fortunate topic that if you
don't do it right you can walk yourself
into some real trouble
where your material might not be usable
by other people
animal different sometime
we'll talk about
hot going through became our section and
a little bit ask you well
writing are aspect files out
and
the in the class so that a lot of stuff
i would like to cover it
we didn't quite get your pet hopefully
at the time we spent
on show you have here it will be a
better sense of how hype on things like
that we spent more time on that then
limit besser played in the beginning but
i think that
is worth the time to you
a little bit more of a man with
otherwise
and i hope we are
provides a good basis for you all to go
about
worrying a lot of other stuff
scores are up with a reminder that
with the center for the class and
courage copying
i'm giving you all permission
to copy modify change to everyone with
this class materials the videos the
audio
basically give you permission to use
this stuff anywhere you like modify it
adult lovett if anybody sends the
changes if you won't find improvements
or
write-up sections i don't have
content for whatever
i will happily put them into the notes
an update them on the material site
the idea of this is that this class
isn't done when you leave here research
tools and sort of a lifelong
and that you'll be wearing stuff as you
go
what we were here isn't the end all be
all of research tools is just
my particular take on all this material
salter impose more videos as we
and was jumping to copyright
is very important to note that this very
first warning
i am not a lawyer
however most lawyers know little about
saw four data
copyright patent issues in this topic
is kinda boring
it's really really important
for example
at you in a chair i was putting up
videos on youtube
i was on travel i got a call from you a
salir he said get everything off of you
to right now
take a call down
and
i didn't know what what was going on
i didn't know why
it took me
several hours of sitting down with the
u_n_'s lawyer
the right to put all my contact back
danny
didn't understand the law they thought
there was all kinds of weird things
going on and we have to sit down and
work for some really ugly issues
in terms of
legal stuff
get the point where the worst understood
that i was allowed to put up you can
videos in that
other faculty and students
are allowed to put a few continues
one of those like it
to seems pretty obvious but
intel the lawyers agree
you don't i think it's do what you want
there are a lot of stuff of lawyers'
candy leading the way
we can also help you out
and anything you see and hear but talk
about copyright before you act on it
legally you should talk to your lawyer
that's the cover my ass part of it
i put a link into the u_s_ copyright
pierre you can read it
but actually has to get information in
it
some of the laws here are different
other countries but a lot of
people at the u_s_ have gone out into
the world and forced u_s_ copyright law
by the country's so
typically things here actually apply a
lot of other places
the key thing to remember
if you don't give somebody copyright
permission somehow
if you don't explicitly give somebody a
license to use what you write to be and
e-mail or otherwise they don't have the
legal rights to use which you do you
so if you create something that is
copyright of all
a painting a picture software
something you right
they don't have the rights to use it eve
if you don't have a copyright sign on it
if you don't face he has a lot of stuff
by creating a in a fixed medium the
email or
putting it into a file
that's a fixed medium
unless you're u_s_ government employees
from some of you
have to do with that aspect
you have a copy right for that
or your employer has the copyright that
we've actually run into some pretty
serious problems with this if someone
says
something is open-source poor public
domain
and they just tell you that
doesn't mean anything
so you actually need to get ally since
two
something from someone else if you want
to use some code or
their writings or date of the big
generated
and if you want to give were stuff to
other people to use for your
collaborating on
some code you need to be very clear and
picked all items of some sort
and write that down
and that will then allow people to work
together and use the material
so for example in my class does that
mean in a creative commons license and
picked up
pick a particular one
bell link here if you really are
insistent on public domain if you're a
federal employee yourself might fall in
the public domain inside the u_s_
but you can try to use this link to make
you're supposed to reunite
suggest not trying to do that because
public domain is very confusing
for anything after august nineteen
seventy two
opensource dot org
has got a whole webpage on
talking about love at first licenses in
this group actually go through licenses
and tries to
evaluate them for you
so if you're looking for a license this
is a place to start
i'll give you my quick recommendations
in a second here but these guys have
a whole list of open-source licenses by
name
you can go through and read lots of
legalese
and i want to show you an example of
something went wrong saddam
you don't need a typing this code i'd
just did it in through the notes so you
can see
g_s_ epigenetic sensor format is a
format used by a lot of so our vendors
people are communities the stairway
transfer information between
software and vendors if you've got sonar
data coming off of one ticker hardware
needed somewhere else be converted she s
f
then it might be portable
remote portable to get
data rounds
jessica's written by it
company called etsy i see
and they're under contract with
the needy however they don't post the
contract so we don't know the details of
what's out there
so if you go grab the source code which
is in
carrots and a high pakistan and the
system in lots of other tools
i went through a private source for this
morning
i unzip it
there are there's that structure is
terrible it dumps files all over the
current directory
agr export license copyright gpl bsd
apache zero
open-source licenses
i actually have read to the co before
trying to find a license
here are red brick command for those
actually i found
quite a few instances of copyright
science applications international
corporation
favor propellant
nowhere in there that i find a license
in their documentation on the web it
says
in quotes this is open source
that doesn't give you the right to use
this code
so people like parents are actually
breaking the law
right now in terms of copyright law
it's up to ask the icy to prosecute if
they want it to you
i don't think they want you and this is
not an intentional
thing going on
if they felt like it they could
get damages from all of these companies
that are using it
you have to be careful about this and
you need to think about
distributing working with people
my hope in this class is you've realized
that
we are international community we want
to collaborate across countries and
boundaries and
companies and
who want to be able to cooperate so we
need to be able to give a license to our
code so that we can work together
so try to avoid things like that
the community at this point is depend on
this column
and they're also hoping that i see i see
it will work with them too
string of licensing
but it's on nobody's radar that's fine
until we're somewhere decides to make it
a mass
a lot of people think that they are not
to worry about that
quite a few software projects over the
years have been
just destroyed by licensing issues
their ben ten fifteen twenty year long
legal battles over software
i don't think our industries at all
interested in any of that stuff we want
to be able to work we don't want to be
fighting over legal junk we just want to
be going out there and clinton cool data
and map in the world
so i'd throw 'em
my recommendation of three common
licenses that you might want to pick if
your
writing some software
there's the berkeley standard
distribution or b_s_t_
that white sands is very flexible it
says basically you can do whatever you
want with my code
you need to acknowledge that i wrote it
you can't use my name for advertising
go forth and use this code
people can resell that coincided things
so there's a lot of b_s_t_ code and all
of your computers using right now
it's really flexible people can do based
or whatever
the algae p_l_o_ or less organ in public
places
version three
basically says if you modify this code
you must
the changes if you give that come to
anybody else
environment four
so if it does is if you write a bunch of
software you want other people to
contribute back to it it's as you know
you get a pain i see every contribute
your changes back to that the main body
but you can put in a commercial tools
that could end up in paris
and you might see a bit say something
like it by some unlikely g sfga turned
into an old gpl project
anytime the carrots folks improved
g_s_ after we've been
have to go out to the community
feminist concept
and the other end of the spectrum is
just pick a new public license
and in that one it says you can use my
code
if you distribute anything
based on that or changed echoed you have
to release it to things like those or
software like terrorists
came to use it
gpl based co
it's more of a political statement in
terms of you wanted
he'd echoed from
going behind closed doors
i tend to you
favor the b_s_t_ in the old gpl license
is because they let more people
collaborate on code
often times i've
gpl base offer weren't getting going
i don't really want to disappear into a
company
i really need some collaboration and to
guarantee that
and then later on off switch it to a
different license to open up what the
coat a little more stable and i don't
mind it to the disappearing into the
company
sinn fein company which is the key
and work on it
past
with b_s_t_ yes
they can make changes to it and you
might not have refused changes if they
did that with l_d_p_ over gpl
unfortunately
suing is usually that recourse you have
which is really no fun nobody wants to
do that
nobody's saying want to do that
religious mechanisms to u communicate
your intentions and hope with people
play along nicely
if you look at
google hosting
once you log in but if you take a look
at the site new login
what it will do is show you some of the
licenses that you can do
they actually restricted to just at
thing feira six different licenses
so i encourage you not to
treat me like this
people everybody's tried that the first
couple years ago iterations of lawyers
working on it usually screw up a lot
even the pros get it wrong
working with licenses and and legal
stuff is really complicated
said don't try to create your own just
pick one of the major ones
wikipedia has a nice little comparison
chart
of going through various licences
europe from when they've been done
how compatible we are because you can
create a license
that such that you can't combine echoed
with any other code that's no good
because
the reason software powerful of the
include bits and pieces together and
create something new
if you really care about life is as you
can go look through those
options
and if you're in the country
you're gonna have to uh...
figure out your own situation yes lives
so yes
if you work
company
patty
quest what's ones you that's fine
do you do it
typically yes university has some
different sections if you're doing
something that is like a journal paper
considered a publication
than you actually human h or not
but yes typically if you're at a company
to do something the company
typically owns almost everything we're
doing
then you talk to a lawyer for the
company and you negotiate how it worked
pretty standard nike here
muddy
before
if you're the one h difficult he
if you're working with gpl code
the code to you right by law has to
become gpl so that's a done deal
working with corn you want to release it
typically that's an issue if you have a
supervisor for two private worry about
and at some point if i don't know
checking a checkbox on u_s_ policy or
talking unit lawyers
typically i consider that with you in
ages its advertising for university we
want to be showing off to cool stuff
that we do as much as possible
playoff us to balance with whether or
not
trying commercialize facto
so some of our code
really we don't see a lot of commercial
potential other coded
that walked up pretty tight because of
so it's pretty confusing
it gets even worse with the lights and
that's because people didn't think about
lessons in data
if i go out and click multimedia
it's mine
don't actually if i give you the file
you don't have the right to do anything
with it
we've had instances where we try to get
their people on their lawyers have said
now you haven't given us permission to
do anything
it was collected under cover of funds
and the stuff
it's open
you really want
and the lawyers that now
cool take that
you you can give us the stated that way
you can't do anything with it
i don't actually know an unseen good
answers
that go along with this drug just posted
some links of things that i found
there's a opened data
commons as vehicle
odp allah license
that's used for openstreetmap
that might be a solution
you can use creative commons licenses
that sort of thing to work
but again you have to be able to give
permissions for that data
and again if you work for company you're
company has to give you the village of
relief that they don't realize that
somebody's going to use it
same case goes for commercial data if
you're working at a contract for me
usually is your contract that good
dictates that that
it can be used very often times you can
walk up together so that no one can ever
use it again and that sucks
watch your own company out of your own
data
that's the worst
there's different licenses for
documentation and tax too
we'll talk about that
if your u_s_ government believe you're
in this really bizarre limbo state
just because of the u_s_ government we
did it
it sometimes means is public domain but
oftentimes it doesn't
there's exceptions and that rule about
how to make only applies inside the
united states
and it may apply elsewhere
but that's questionable
so if you're
government bullying you create something
you might actually on the copyright back
in other countries
little bit cleared
and government funding again like if
it's an s_l_ funding and supposed to be
released
you may be contractually required to
lease it
release under certain license
or you may not
it's very hard to follow these things
and we don't have good answers to
but to do with this
and the contract officers don't even
understand some of these rules
themselves
so it's a little bit confusing
in one last copyright thing to talk
about
there's a concept that very few people
seem to use that i think might be a
great solution for
when you guys go out you may be working
in contract forms or
creating contract for contract firms to
do data collection or write source code
for you
you should consider things
called escrow
previously say hey we're gonna
use of third parties or not but that's
worth kotor data
in the store
and what you hear hang onto it for a
certain number here say five years in
them a make it public domain or
release under some license
or you can say
your alternate issue if you're working
with people who want close to write
closed source
stuff for her bday today
is locked up as you can say
well as long as you're still producing
that software
company acts
you know where it will work with you but
you'd better put that's all for an
asteroid if you ever go out of business
restart making that product
we have it for free forever
if you create licenses like that one
year
fish if you're a big government agency
creating contracts
you can put in whatever you can legally
pull off in there
you can basically put protections in
their such that if the company
goes bankrupt
which happens or they get bought out by
somebody who is interested in your
product that you've been using
if you're using a multi process off
where and that company gets far up apart
their technology
because microsoft and google or yahoo
when they buy that
and say we don't really want that
software respect kill it
would you gonna do
that's offer just goes to prove
and license keys right now
you really in trouble
but if you can put in
in your contracts awaits you say
if you ever do that we have a software
for free forever
that gives you extra protection in the
it may be really painful to go through
with that
and you may have to hire people who
understand how to work with that code
these are ways you might be able to
protect yourself a little bit more
down the road
if your contract for me
you want to show up what you do but i've
worked with people who've never been
able to show me anything that they do it
after what i paid them for
because everything else is walked up and
contracts
if you wanna show off
how great your most indians
you could put in your license if you can
call off in the negotiations
haiti after five years
i need to be able to show this let's put
it in the the world archives and want to
use this data for other stuff
but you know what
we understand that is proprietary for
that people x years that need to hold
onto this
so what's up by their side
and will release its suny twenty twenty
that they will get released
and that'll become a part of the
scientific commons
but until then will hold onto it
for those kinds of agreements
i don't see that happening very often
but they could be really powerful may
could be a way to balance
the commercial interest that you need to
do u with
preservation of
this important data
actor in a week for my company i know
nothing about
but they're actually nascar service
so you can see contact this company that
third party
and there are a legal contract they
won't release whatever it is a holding
onto until certain things and that might
be a time release or
some sort of contract agreement
so those are some
things i think about
really not agree topic it's not very fun
we're here to do science dot copyright
law
and deal with all those conditions but
if we don't do what the we can get
ourselves when we stopped
i've written actually a lot of source
code that will never be legally
releasable
because of these issues they were
written
at a government facility as a contractor
and things are so
confused that nobody knows how to
release that code legally
and if we don't have a four day and we
might have had a chance that it would
have been a big deal
sonar copyright stuff
this is my sabb list of things that i
want to show you guys that i think are
really cool
you'll have to come back we'll plead for
some videos later on
one of them does have a video
so you took a real just to check out
the class notes
in their i've gone through the basics of
creating a mercurial project it's a
about thirty-five minutes were actually
just a tiny little bit of material
there's a lot more
and thirty-five minutes is not enough to
really did you guys
deeply involved with that i was hoping
that
photo-op throughout the whole semester
but i realize pretty quickly that we
we covered a lot of material
you guys did pretty well covering it for
how much we did but need always like to
have more in there
it takes time to get used to things like
revision control and how do you work
with stuff
i thought it was really cool because we
have sixteen students plus a couple
orders here
we could have done
commits emergent have
a dock in the military to gather if it's
my hope
trick renew class and work that in and
we've just been too much so i didn't go
for it time sorry
geol map out
is a great tool for finding data
maybe i can convince the geo map out
team at lemont oriented to make it
easier themselves normally get
and your good willy from their team to
come up and give a great
seminar but we are just jam packed for
material
so these things didn't quite make it
i feel like
what we've gone through a spend more of
the basics building the foundations of
the things that you guys are not ready
to dig into and
it's no
so i'm hoping that you guys feel more
comfortable going out learning about
these these tools
using
improve our nasa world wind
collecting data
with pipe on using high cereal to talk
to serial port subs who can do that
that we have some people here at c_ come
who are very good at that
role in his uh...
especially notable for
doing data logging with pipeline
ap projecting and processing data with
proj ingi dot you guys salt and very
briefly but we missed a lot of it
the capabilities
using python the defeated the matlab in
our g_i_s_ carriage type act where mousa
g_m_t_
it's a great glue language for sticking
things together
so even though some these tools don't
have i'd bum dope that you can still
for example
work with later mouse you can take the
data again former player mouse once
part time just i have not ruled in a
quick scripting in there
will take things you can let them around
and one huge thing that i had
very sorry i missed was our plan to do
tidied a processing
contends that has written all kinds of
tools to help you guys out with your
summer hydro project
and i didn't cover them im really sorry
python is a great way to you quickly
process
millions of data points enough to bring
them into excel and try to suffer
through the more full spreadsheet saying
and in pa classes with actually the past
years
the students have used
fight on the process the data from the
tide station then draw engineers and get
it ready
and do the averaging to get to the six
minute form testified
terrace to meet the known standards and
to your
accurate picture of it
so i'm hoping to be able to
pull that off in the next six months ago
you guys the video from the west coast
to do that but i'm not sure what to do
it fan is still in the building so
i would highly recommend talking to ban
about his titles before you get your
summer hydro
so that's why didn't cover i'm very
sorry apologize profusely
let's go do some more python
a little bit of time
analyst jump in
give it a go
worked again here
hopefully guys still have
artsy update
which will do your mercurial update
which you have probably argued before
you came in the room
before i got in
and so they're probably no updates
available
if you your elise doesn't work i've
actually putting the commands that will
do the same thing
and c_d_s into their research tools
directory that range deformities see
update
so let's go ahead and get ourselves into
a directory where we can work with the
stuff
so make your filled with slash class
twenty six if you haven't already done
that
i've already got it
sito's flash
class twenty-six
dvd
i was in the wrong directory which is
good that i did that to me and
black sheep all the notes
if you want to create a bookmark for it
victim bookmark
c twenty six
and just make sure
bookmark
dash adult
because he was not a class twenty four
in a class twenty-six bookmark
yet again since the power in this
building likes to hit up
long starts dash ho dash our laws
twenty-six apart
slice of the law twelve was for
factory were
let's go grab our aspect files again
today should be
tired of hearing me
talk about caroll interviewed yet
so pace that in
copy
so now if we do in our style show you'll
see there should be some visa files
weekend beyond zip with those three
commands
and if we do in our special again you
should see that we've got
are three aspect to play with
rather than copying and pasting and some
giant i compile this is
going to get you exactly the code that i
had last time
so if you do you
this copy this will copy from the
cure-all posit o-ring
and go ahead and corporate profile
trolex controller
till the slash class
twenty-six
have that top right
and we're back to you working on
decoding the planet's pos pac asked that
i mean you find any box
so we were working on k amount
few classes ago
written up quick script to do it but we
had some data points in our aspect files
that were out zero zero
that great garbage dump
study likes to go
and we want to get those
out of
our data
so we need to add some code in there
that will actually remove those era zero
point is we're reading through they
don't want to skip anything that's right
around zero zero
if you're ever surveyor at their their
own let me know how that goes
if you're in a multi been survey across
there i bet all kinds of softball
crashes freaked out
we have uh... a lot of
got a lot of problems going across the
dateline or
the uh...
zero out of the longitude
adeptly we had a research proves that
went back and forth across the dateline
down by an article and every time we did
that behind you crashed
it was really i'm fine
papers uh... one lesson this clock
should teach you is
ask questions often and always
the aggressive about
getting help when you get stuck
otherwise things get harder and harder
if you go down without having
past the question
so the first thing we need to do is we
have floating-point numbers
and other trouble because
a floating point number doesn't always
equal the same floating point number
because of running problems
so be safe at created this function
called almost equal
basically look for range around a point
soap week toward preparing for a number
here
and up form
that you can be
either side up if you're in this range
and this is your point you compare
number in the max within that tolerance
you consider those numbers the same
and in python there's actually an
absolute on giving to u that they think
is good
sourcesafe import
sis
and sis dot
float
info
inside there it is
applaud
you hit enter
after importing sess
what phyto spells an affluent should be
on this computer
you can always pick your own
but dissident one that seems to work
pretty well
luciano function that does this
comparison but what could be sloppy
so if you're close to zero but not in
fact the added he should be executed
yourself at zero
so this function ever written right here
will compared to values
and he is an excellent for a look at the
values
greater than value coupons out form
it'll say no
these are the same if the value is less
than
the second value minus epsilon return
false otherwise say yep they're pretty
much the same
so this is the kinds of things you
create functions for and fight on
a capsule ate some little idea that
you need to put this in your court of
returning to compare vertical crazy
suffragist copy this code
w
to destroy and who put that right
below d
from people and importantly printed
above the pilgrims
say that
now we need to go and use that code
inside of our lives where we are looking
data grams
so that you need to use that
almost equal down in are
function that we are working on and
i have looked at the since last time so
i'll be a little surprised when i see
the code man looked at it for two weeks
so inside of our four datagram
so here's what we're looking forward
trying to find
the beginning of our for literally leapt
over the data
so it's in your world aspect file
function
int if u group here
in select load aspect file it'll jump
you write about function
or you can be like a control left and
search for
four datagram
so it could take a look and there
and we need to do
is ad
this almost equals in here
uh... my within the wrong place them
yes we can get main
boy this is what happened here
yeah i example of that
so probably want that
in both places
both in the main pernell
to catch
so search for the main
because you know i a m fight on
and inside of maine
that for datagram in index
andrey here we have a out dot right
road out
align
for idea
so right there
should be about lying
three hundred and fourteen if you look
great here at the line number
you can search for line three fourteen
so go ahead and have that in
almost
equal
zero point
and our acts
almost equal
uh...
of hesitant oaks you that's not good
statistically speaking to you mixture
your remained
old point
some people don't leaving around it
i'd say the bugging america like that
one of her strange
that's not good
okay call
so i numbers are not helpful in my case
wine rapping in buffer a rapid window
extricate
so going to maine and find that
so you're looking for
before datagram index inside of me
well i think if you do the right spot
i don't know what your colors are really
messed up
yet more if you have a quote
that didn't finish traded you out
figure three close those kids
immediately to those three quotes right
yes sony which is you have to quote
ending triple courtney star uh... feelin
according to quote your entire file
that's a good one
those of the others are hard to figure
out
so zero point com a
and wife
so what we've done it said before
right about zero zero
we wanted to skip that
point we don't wanna right now so we can
say continue
and that continues could jump back up to
the top of fourth and keep going
so if we say that
and we tried it hopefully will be able
to read it came out back to make sense
and you guys can copy that your desktop
and you okay mellow out where the
suspect filers
so troublesome warned
was that i believe
the two thousand eleven data
so if we save ron
aspect dot pint
and twenty eleven
thought aspect
hopefully but will begin to you is
does just help
so just let the by the file names
so this is the great thing about having
helped
written into your code
we haven't used it and will bet you
might forget your own code
so we can say two thousand eleven
pressed tab
it should list out your aspect
later in the did uh... that okubo
were to help come from all working but
uh...
twenty for
that helped you
with army floating here and there was
only a dash eight option and then we
specify filings okay
so not a lot to the uh... this is for a
pretty boring
in his class i should have just as a
father was
pretty mild term he was doing but
operate codeplex eighty million options
and then i have to remember how to use
them
so i'm not going to try to run it will
steve explodes
it's completely unhappy
so i'll show you a little bit the
booking
yeah it's not going to work
uh...
yes correct
so what i've done as i looked at the
struggle owners acts and wine
four of you but you might sample in the
notes which is actually point the wrong
place
in this context
datagram long datagram flat
we need to follow the same pattern ads
right below it
here we have x and y defined
but what we need to do is replaced that
connections to these two guys
w
and we can just say
corrected king live
pet pic status
i say datagram acts
performed for you
so we going to do is
pull those two journal does x and y
it's a stopping i played this what you
want to put datagram long datagram
degrees down here in new york code but
that should work
and if i a rerun this
it should go
so that those two bands
uh... so what you may be doing is you're
writing divers in the pregnant and
you're working on two different piles of
different locations and having abortions
problem
so once a different place
if you control like the look like to
move it local people are working to
sample
hooking up until it's in the cake
job offers
presenter
and then do a files and bounds
and make sure it's yet with at the cost
twenty six say you're a landing profile
does and when you're running
i think you have cds you let me say this
deal where you were one point
if you want to not show there zero zero
ones
well just
yemeni hope that's a great question i'll
show you why that's happening itself
so if you look in your printout you're
actually still seeing zero zero shear
also present heart
doesn't make a lot of sense
if you look at were continuance
here's our checked for continuing
and here we use that model operator
printout every twenty eight datagram to
the screen
if we
move back so control space
commence once controlled all of you
could put that right above it
so yank that
control y
and we switch the order so we did talk
before we do that for now
and we're here on our script
anyone and zero zero disappears
that make a little more sense
now if we do an ally special will see
that there should be a came out file
somewhere here instances wrapping for
her to see
so if we do a less
twenty eleven
and you're right up there
throw the point where shows the aspect
but we also other aspect dot k miles
but i have a report of that city
it
that's why i called classes before they
go out don't worry
so do a less if i cannot file
and you should now see
insider forgetting should see about a
quarter for setup
and uh... a greater then we'll take you
to the bottom of the file and laughs
and then you can take you to quit out
and now if you want to see that
you can copy of her to the windows live
because
who worked as a little bit clunky
say what you can do
copying
twenty eleven
aspect k amount like that
every throw in our dropbox you can go
back to your drop box for how many of
you forgot your drop box password since
last time
used to it
statement
effecting your table file okay
polyether thought that you cannot file
yeah
so do a good choice one else echo
interlock script
superior main function
so typically with python you can get any
trouble with
inventing
so take a look
see how i have my ex white datagram up
on the screen
online and then the prep aladdin almost
equals
knows that the inventing easily seen
column
so this guy is back and and it's all
parades forward
so good
godown senior almost people's anti back
in one more
and then delete
that this one
so see how that palace in the same
and then you put a continual on the next
one
between uh... if in the house
you see how it's working
it's helpful
copied
yet it's kind of all americans but yatin
at the heart
yet it's happening in the hopes that you
can if you can't have it will help for
faculty through
it's hard to learn how to read the
inventing and want to get used to adjust
our pick it up
to try to run again
so if i copied it
i'm going to overwrite one i really have
there
so yes
and i'm a switch how for this to fight
on
and open tools slash
dropbox twenty eleven
underscore
and hopefully drop boxes are numerically
synced everything
we go back to norfolk
and we mow the lawn
for those you don't know the turmoil in
the line
this is typically the party to any
surveying too
to get full coverage and if the same
thing you do when you go out and
do with the grass in your yard
thing called mowing the lawn
now in order to use
google earth we need to use it from
windows
so rollin inside the virtual machine you
want to be using ideal or firefox on
windows
and then going into your dropbox account
ended i cannot buy out from the drop box
account
was put my window and go back to
notes
so it's great that we have a came off i
don't
databases
how you're going to databases in fifteen
minutes
at the bar because this is a really
great topic
really deserves
a couple classes rather than
just a couple methods
i won at least heavy seas
doing some database work
if we don't get very much done
others show you a little bit about
databases
think of it as kinda like a spreadsheet
way more programmable
it works more like coating were
spreadsheets are really not coating
in the normal times
if things they disappear behind
one of your squares to appreciate
with databases that works on tables
there for like a spreadsheet world that
might be one of your happens
and kids they create table
i have a little if not exist so if you
are in the second time table doesn't
get upset that is turning creeks and
cable
and i have a table name called aspect
entry
acceptable it looks very light which is
you can all the stuff we're doing is
just mentally translating between the
vocabulary and one
and look at doing another
hopefully easier than learning a foreign
language
but because it is a similar concept of
four lines were you just switching
vocabulary
the vocabulary case we have here is that
these are variable names are going to
have a neat row
in our big table
we call them doubles are floats in other
spaces
therefore anti-piracy here's my language
floating-point numbers and gave a circle
for to israel
if revoke ever comes from fort ran in
the nineteen fifties
but the real number i guess
mathematical term
i like twenty point lead
so bizarre all reels
you could have a lot of other detectives
strings
you need to have all sorts of different
things in here but we just are gonna
have
a bunch of floating point number of the
throw
and we can then insert roseanne that
database
and then we can give them in firefox
the firefox as myself again that makes
it look like a spreadsheet insight into
the database
so i'm gonna go ahead and pat
creation too
uh... but if you like to debase to our
i'm gonna go pretty fast rarely show it
to you
so i'm gonna create function that
goes through
and creates
takes aspect file
anne watching right out that has that
file
uh... database
so we walk you through really quick
what's here
of copied into the code so we can
actually see it have an impact on
minedu rate above the main
pace dot in
and there's some funny terminology
inside databases that you have to use to
you
the first ones we're gonna grab the
module that knows how to talk to the
database
for each database typist typically uh...
a model that goes with it
there's a lot of different databases
theirs
ask you why it is a simple wonder post
grass
there's mysql that microsoft access
and siebel server
they go out on this might have heard of
oracle
things like that
warranties one has built in the pipeline
askew light
that i think that he liked is it
the debate is just the file
so within the other ones are complicated
had some big server unwanted paint
version of the person
jain salary to maintain the database if
he's oracle
but have to fight is a great way to
start with super simple
compared the other ones
the first thing you do with databases
you connect to it
so will say ask you light three
and the freemen version three rescue
light
and connect to a database and then the
file name not a creator filed in the
directory
that'll be our database
where it creates the table
we're just going to work with a couple
variables
we didn't really need to apo revolving
restaurant which is one display like the
x_y_z_ of our shift
and no time unless we can ignore the
fact that this
sees a create table if exists
and then our cable main suspect entry
cameras that have time
y axis the
and
explosive
it's going to write me crazy that's why
i expect
this was our generator
that returns
i'd datagram each time they've been
through our file
and really use the enumerate
so you give a number for each one
so we have our datagram index that is
going to get that humor read accounts so
preventable keep going up it's time for
it
the datagram mistake it
a dictionary back
from are loathe aspect file for each
datagram
in database languages you execute
commands
and wonderfully as you can do is insert
into
which basic reason you role in this
table
you get back to talent which
parts of that
bro you when i had to sell time
x_y_z_
uh... i'll
so i've got to y axis pictures alright
i've swapped it cuz i write x_y_z_
so this have to then and values match
through times of the expired pills can
and then altitude is arsie
and then you pass it
this dictionary so this is kind of doing
a funky lookup
working for the call and then the name
inside of your
dictionary here getting back it'll go
and look up that dictionary value and in
turn into here
have a common theme in pipeline
be able to look at things by means you
don't have to know that it's like the
third entry in there
and then there's a weird concept in
database is where you commit
which basing his you're working on the
database
and so you say commit it won't actually
save that
i don't know how many times
worked really hard prison code
and i look at the results of a basement
nothing in it
because i forgot to commit i don't think
it
so that's our code to create this
database
every go ahead and have a option into
our command line person that we can say
dash dash as fuel a panel reaganesque
you like in a sports
so that's a lot in a couple minutes
but hopefully give you just a sense of
the flavor of
databases
soman go back to the notes
in here says add this to the main
functions are going to add a
command-line options
on inside of me
had treated this person that is our
command line thing and we haven't had
any real options we just use it to grab
our file names
which you had another option here
so we can say
parser
dot ad
arguments
dash dash ask you liked
there's lots of different types of
arguments you can have a cat true false
that if you see that flag over core that
it's all right
or you can actually have numbers in
there that will do
began and say
action
people's store
true
and them into the default is false
so that will happen is when we run are
command-line arguments
hill the faulty being false
that we want to learn a skill i file but
if we specified absent as to why now
become true in the making cuts that
later on and right
database
so now if we say iran
dot pine
dash dash
will see if my coat blows up but i think
i pause again this time
and i haven't
mode dot here's another option
down there if it says that dash askew
lights
give any help suffering i still say
help equals
writes
askew lights
database
and uh... strength
so now we do help
we have a new option dash dash right
askew like database
buzzfeed brave
and try to run it
course iran
and then control our research back
through our history
here's the one i have before so i can
say
dash dash askew lights
please write me a database
and the press answered
iran's really fast great
do you think there'll be a database file
waiting for us
there should be nephew light
file somewhere in here and i don't see
one
we uh... didn't do anything with that
command-line argument that we had
so we actually have to glue the two
together
so if we take a look here
in the four loop
we have some code here
will go through it will look move into
our pollens actually caller aspect to
ask you lights
photo add that into our for loop for
each file
so here we have our
for filing
so right after that for live
we can say
args dot
askew likes
if that's true
we want to write an aspect
to uh... masculine
sql
file name
filename
plus and then
sitting not overwrite my datafile which
i've done too many times
flag on an extension of bounces dot
askew light
save itself for every time we have a
file
if we have that
be true
we can then
write out a file
and also help ourselves
so here we print out the file names let
me just print out
askew lights
question mark
args
testified
so what i want to do is to show you you
should see a true or false coming out
sophie run it
without the dash
dash askew light
right up here gil csd like false
so nope didn't want to write ask you
light
we do it one more time
with the dash dash askew light
will see a true
and hopefully a call that function and
rode out something
and there it is
so if we say bang tourist children file
eleven
aspect of askew lights
and actually knows this is an ask you
light
three point x database
that's great
right now we'll look at it from a few
nice exit author david
firefox
actually has a nice plugin for it
and is it installed
so if you don't have as good major
installed you would go to
add-ons
to add ons search
for askew lights
it works the way
and you're listening to her because i
already have installed so it should
actually be the first option in here
so up in the top right
under nexus tools this is the search
when they're just had to ask you light
up the top right
and the very first document shows up if
you don't have installed and as he like
manager
go ahead and get install
over here with
for about option
i see a number of you've got up there
and
since because so much that goes with the
process to install it
and then you have to restart firefox
it's a common problem with plugins as
you give it a go
you think you've installed it
and i think they're doesn't do anything
yep actually restart firefox
nundi tools askew like mentor
and it's unhappy about something because
i was looking at all databases
doesn't exist
you won't see that i hope
so don't there's a couple options appear
the three fresh this new database if you
want to create
database here it'll help until the
database
connected database that's what i
actually want to do
sing the go ahead and connect to the
sign
and now it facing uh... directory tree
full of stuff
along with another class
since which by name
icy class repaired
we got a lot of classes down sick last
twenty six
ends or their savings and investment
like if you don't have that you can
select on files
but doesn't look like we want him
north yet you have to do to get to go
into tables for the database qasar might
be many tables so doesn't know which one
to show you
inside there is a expecting treat
and show you the roads that are in there
you select dot
here are
your database roads
and you can sort on
melanie coleman typical aps
through the spreadsheet set up
and your date is in there
so now if you want to talk about it in a
more spreadsheet form
you've actually got way to play with it
and you can actually
executing tryout
commands
and if you want were asked who else is
not a bad place to try
if he generator finder escalated a basic
contracts and commands
so from aspect
entry
and i know that
limited specifies how many i print out
and hopefully if i save ron we get ten
so that's one example of using ask your
plan to return stuff so select star says
give me everything from this table
and if we only want to see
x calmer winds
wilson rescue el nino zacks com ally and
that is not enough about databases to
really feel comfortable with it
but at least
behaved as to where to start
and the great thing about davis's
there's name columns
if you're working with someone you can
just send that file so here was a nasty
white file
you can just zip dot upper compress it
somehow
stick it on the email send somebody drop
it on a few peter any transfer the debt
and they'll know their names the tables
the vacancy in the school
so terrible table that could explain to
them
don't know that
the names of the columns
with her at that final the raw data
we had to be able to write a purse or
read the note was an aspect of
somebody's give you file called through
that happen to be aspect
if you were familiar of aspects because
i have a lock there's no way to gas
furnace that file
really that it's an estate files just
for binary data
it's very
uniformed floating-point numbers it
could be almost anything in their if you
didn't know what it was
so this way with somebody sends you ask
you a file he does open up here and you
can see it in and get a sense port right
away there's no like
i gotta go write some crazy perjuring
use this truck commander first binary
data and
hope where there's a specification
somewhere on the web but i can't find a
defined format and three days later you
can read the data
here if you can see it you can decide
idu are don't want to use this is
healthier don't help me with my project
and we're good to go
flats databases in
uh... degree expense fifteen minutes for
twelve minutes there
waging fast singers actions and
documentation in the general directory
on the web page for the class
that will be it for research tools
i hope it's been helpful you guys
it's that kind of material
trip leaking out your years about now
and about to go into finals
the the material is still here refer to
copy that i will try to make a zip of
the whole class that you can just
download it'll be a couple hundred
megabytes but you'll be able to alan two
videos the audio
and all the class goes just in one file
and if you nigger desi described a file
ticket with you to materials helpful and
you can work through that your own
right guys
welcome the sea calm dots research tools
therefore the research
your last summer kissimmee homework five
and i'll put up opposed
i work for you had to go to term one in
a while back and you know that
deluxe one it'll be a stone work
partnership of about ten or quality such
instructions again
recently
will be on the research tools computer
so there should be aight
an entry for every day and that file up
three today and then that's the end
now i thought every day of the week
that's just a few facts